Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Massieu, -----. Caen
    Wrote to Mr. Deane in the beginning of April concerning M. Dumesnil de St. Pierre who was killed three years before in the service of Congress and of whose death some authentic certificate is wanted; encloses an extract of his letter to Mr. Deane as the best way to explain the affair; begs for an answer.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    His interviews with the Grand Facteur à propos of the advisability of presenting to the Grand Pensionnaire a copy of the treaty with France. Has just seen the fine, spirited Resolution of Congress on the subject of the Conciliatory Bill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 11; A.L.S. 1p. Enclosing a sketch of this plan (3 p.). 1p.; Georgelin du Cosquer, Barthélemy-Pélage. Paris
    His project for duration of law-suits in France; hopes Franklin will second his undertaking; Article 25 of the wise Constitution of Pennsylvania is the model which he intends to propose to France for imitation.
    Copy of Franklin's answer. Avows his attachment to France; praises M. du Cosquer's laudable intention, but pleads his ignorance of French law as a reason for his being unable to judge of the work. 1p.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780?] [May?] 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Assuring franklin of her friendship. Advantages of friendship over love. Places implicit trust and confidence in Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Arrival of the frigate Boston, Captain Tucker, from Bordeaux; she will sail the next day in company with the frigate L'Oiseau.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Acknowledging the punctuality with which his drafts have been honored. Causes for the high price of fresh beef.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Acknowledging their favor of the 25th ult. Will transmit every month whatever disbursements his department may receive and will communicate any ocurrences meriting attention.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Introducing the bearer, Captain Casstle; he and his wife desire to return to Philadelphia; the Captain's business in Paris is to obtain the restitution of a ship belonging to him and his brother; if he succeeds, will make her American property and procced at once to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard. Manheim
    At Franklin's request made inquiries about Richard Cooke, a native of Rotterdam; he has been living in North Carolina, but starts for Europe with letters to Franklin, with the intention of looking after the legacy, said to have been left him. Acknowledging Franklin's letters.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Archer, H. Paris
    Though a native of England, it is his wish to go to America and enter into one of the regiments of horse; will be glad to serve at first as a volunteer at his own expense. Inveighs against Great Britain; expresses the greatest admiration for America. Proposes to wait on Franklin in company with Baron de Ridberg.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Harcken, Johann Wilhelm. Hamburg
    Offers his services as clergyman. Asks free passage to America for himself and family.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 15; L.S. 1p.; Whipple, Abraham. Paimboeuf
    Acknowledging their favor per Captain Jones; desires orders relative to his prisoners; his masts being prepared; offers to carry arms and clothing to the United States.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Question of presenting the treaty still pending; attitude of the Grand Facteur.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Lee., 1778 June 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre
    Surprised at receiving no information of the Treaty of Commerce concluded between France and America. As agent for the United States in the West Indies, cannot discharge his duties with any credit to himself or his country, if he is to be kept in ignorance of such important information.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Captain Conyngham's arrival at Corunna from Cadiz, having captured four prizes on the way. The Jersey privateers still continue on the coast of Spain; news of other vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 16; A.L.S. 5p.; Salvator, Antoine. Cadiz
    Begging his acceptance of a small work (poem) as a proof of his ardent and active interest in America. His intense admiration for Franklin, Washington and the new Republic. Certain rumors current as to why the Spanish fleet has not arrived.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of June 5th, relative to the exchange of prisoners; transcribes his own letter of June 5th on the same subject, for fear it may have miscarried.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 17; L.S. 8p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Concerning the account Mr. Pringle gave him of his interview with Franklin; takes great offense at some of Franklin's expressions. No attention has ever been paid to his repeated requests to be told why all knowledge of the treaty with France was withheld from him; considers Franklin's reasons for his conduct are not the true ones; tells him what he thinks were his real motives. Arthur Lee's chivalrous defense of Franklin in the day of his tribulation and his ungrateful return. Wishes to know if it is true that the French ministry desired that Mr. Arthur Leee and himself should be kept in ignorance of certain matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 17; Diss. M. 8p.; -------, -------
    Remarks on the political situation in England during the war with the American Colonies. The interests of the other European powers will impel them to oppose England in this war. Sees no prospect of England being able to subdue the Colonies and thinks she should attend to her affairs at home. Would be folly for her to declare war against France or Spain in the present state of her affairs.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Astonished at their refusal of offers on the part of certain vessels to cruise against the English, at their own expense and under the laws of the American navy; the principal promoter of this enterprise is an old associate of the Marquis Roux of Corsica, well-known for his audacity and courage.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Desires an answer to his letter of the 8th inst. Concerning the two vessels now being fitted out for America, which will carry letters and any news they may care to send. Contradictory reports as to the whereabouts of the English squadron. Certain American seamen who are in distress and claim protection; advises their being helped, otherwise they are sure to go over to Great Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Laubertie, Victoire. Brunswick
    Concerning Colonel de Donup who, before his death, sent to one of his friends at Kassel, 8,000 ćcus to be placed to the credit of his children, who are also hers and whom he legitimatized before his departure for America; this sum of money detained by the Council of War at Kassel; begs Franklin to find out if Colonel de Donap did not leave a will in America in favor of his children, in order that they may not be deprived of all his effects.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    From certain reports, believes that Admiral Keppel's squadron was seen off Portland the 15th inst. Rumor that Lord Byron's squadron sailed from Plymouth the 10th inst. Refusal of a French vessel to carry to America, as passenger, James Bearus who was wounded while on board the Lexington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Lovell, James. Yorktown
    Forgot to forward the Resolve of May 5th with the ratifications of the treaties. The American troops entered Philadelphia on the 18th; the intention of the enemy in evacuating it not yet explained. Commissioners will be particularly nominated to transact affairs at Lisbon and The Hague, if those courts are well-disposed toward America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 21; A.L.S. Richard Henry Lee, Tho[ma]s Heyward, James Lovell. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Yorktown
    Arrival of the British Commissioners; an answer to their propositions is printed in the Pennsylvania Gazette of the 2oth inst. General Clinton's evacuation of Philadelphia on the 18th; General Washington is pursuing the enemy into Jersey. Desire the most exact information concerning the authenticity of Mr. Holker's mission to Congress, touching their treaty with Great Britain.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Moore, William. Paris
    Petition for a pass.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 22; A.D.S. 1p.; Joy Castle and William Castle, of Philadelphia. Passy
    Petition for papers to permit them to proceed to America with a cargo.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Powers, Peirce. Brest Hospital
    Was midshipman on board the Ranger in her action with the Drake; lost his right arm and received a bad wound in his left hand; being unable any longer to serve his country, desires to be proved with a passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Masson, -----. Paris
    Saw with pleasure in the Courier de l'Europe, a translation of the famous latin verse, which so truly applies to Franklin; thinks the translation, though good, lacks the brevity of the original; his rendering is:
    "Il arracha par ses rares talents
    La foudre aux dieux, le sceptre aux tyrans."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Eclat with which the Marquis d'Almadora is received by the chief officers of Bordeaux; expects his residence in London will be a short one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 23; Montresor, Sir Francis. Bordeaux
    Has been very busy fitting out the Vengeance; account of her guns, crew, etc. His attachment to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Veuve Lalanne et fils. Bayonne
    Concerning one of their vessels, L'Esp"érance, which was captured in a mainfestly illegal manner by the Captain of the Nottingham and whose cargo they hope to be able to recover with Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Boylston, John. London
    Pictures Franklin at the helm in these stormy times, the thunder rattling round his head and securely shrouded under his own intellectual rod of fortitude and truth. Hopes the enclosed will be of some service to their unhappy townsfolk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Mather, Samuel. Boston
    Congratulating Franklin on the success of his prudent and faithful negotiation. Promising aspect of things in the New World; the success of General Gates against " the pompous, histrionical Burgoyne" has communicated no small terror to the enemy. His experiences in Boston during the siege. Is seventy-two years old; hopes before his death to see his country peacefully established in the happy state of liberty and independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Gaulay, -----. Strasbourg
    Desires to enter the service of America in the capacity of surgeon; his past experience.
    A.E. by Franklin. Has no orders to send surgeons to America and can therefore give him no encouragement.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Ford, Hezekiah. Nantes
    Reasons why he has decided to take passage on board Mr. Ross's schooner bound to Virginia. Thanking him for the letter of recommendation. His indignation at the cruelty which has lately marked General Howe's conduct in wantonly destroying the property of individuals up the Delaware. Anathematizes George III.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Droüet, -----. Paris
    Has been occupied for forty-two years on a plan, which, while it assures the growth of power to a nation, promises at the same time a real and lasting well-being to its people; the work has been immense, but the summary is finished; desires to read it to Franklin in order to obtain his opinion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 26; A.L.S. 3p.; La Plaigne, Emmanuel-Pierre de. Plymouth
    An account of their being attacked, on May 1st, by the corsair Lively and obliged, after a sharp fight, to surrender; treated like savages, ironed and imprisoned; his relations and domestics dependent on his aid while he is reduced to the lowest misery; begs for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 26; 1p.; -----,-----
    In praise of Dr. Franklin and M. Dubourg. Verses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 26; L.S. 1p.; Girardot, Haller and Co. Paris
    Begging for letters of recommendation on behalf of Mr. Solomon Kitt, a gentleman of good family in Germany, who desires some protection in America, for which country he has the sincerest attachment. Entreats him to answer their repeated letters for Messrs. Dubbeldemutt, of Rotterdam.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Concerning the engagement of "La Belle Poule" and its possible consequences. America does not appear to be Admiral Byron's destination. Hopes the arrival of good news in America may promote the recruiting service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Forestier, — de. Hesdin
    Concerning a man in town who calls himself de Bonne and who professes to be a captain in the service of the United States; his past unsavory record; thinks he will throw discredit on the service, therefore writes Franklin this warning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 27; L.S. 2p.; Thompson, John. Brest
    Was wounded in an engagement with an English vessel whilst gunner on the Lexington. Lost his leg and is in the hospital at Brest. Appeals to Franklin for money and clothing.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Account of his presenting the treaty to the Grand Pensionnaire. Expected arrival of M. Van Berkel. Reported loan of three million florins raised by Holland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 27; L.S. 2p.; Poreau and Co. Dunkirk
    Concerning a bond which they are to sign and which they hear is to be presented to them by Mr. Coffyn; sorry to tell Franklin that he is a most improper person for such a trust; begs that the bond may be sent by another hand.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Whipple, Abraham. Nantes
    Expects to be able to sail by the 20th of July; if he is to take any goods on board, would be glad to know of it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 27; A.L.S. 2p.; de Romas, -----. Agen
    Remembering the correspondence that Franklin had with his brother, takes the liberty to ask his influence with M. le Prince de Montbarrey to obtain letters exempting his nephew from examinations at the school of Mezières; wishes to bring his nephew to call on Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Teissier, Le Sieur
    Reminds Franklin that he was presented to him by the Comte de Sarsfield; is about to sail for America to offer his services as surgeon to the United States; begs for the promised letter of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 28; D.S. 1p.; Parson, Samuel
    Certificate as to the diligence, skill, and modesty of Chevalier de La Neuville, and his brother Major Normont de La Neuville, Inspector and Deputy Inspector of the army under General Gates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Account of the arrival of the frigate Oiseau with the prize Hope, a privateer, which had taken the brig Sally, of Massachusetts; gives the names of the sailors from Marblehead who were prisoners on board; procured their liberty and sent them to join Captain Jones of the Ranger.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Amiel, Peter. Nantes
    Captain Jones has granted him leave to stay at L'Orient to settle his private affairs; since then, has been offered apartments in the the chateau of M. de Chaumont; begs for an extension of leave.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Lalanne, -----. Paris
    Desires to know if the two propositions made to Franklin have met with any success.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. The Commissioners have no authority to purchase wine for America, nor, as yet, to appoint consuls.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Hiriart, ------. St. Sebastian
    Has read in the papers a latin verse which ought to be put at the foot of Franklin's portrait; suggests a slight emendation; this is his first attempt in poetry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Ford, Hezekiah. Paimboeuf
    Account of an engagement between two privateers belonging to the state of Connecticut, and two British men-of-war, ending in a victory for the Americans. Fears to return to Virginia in Mr. Ross's schooner on account of the numerous cruisers now on the coast.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    A vessel from Louisiana reports the seizure, by the back settlers of Georgia and Carolina, of all British posts on the banks of the Mississippi, together with two valuable vessels laden for London. Other captures reported. Count d'Aranda's passage through Bordeaux on his return journey from Madrid to Paris.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 June 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Information received of the arrival in England of six Russian ships-of-war and the expected advent of six more; the captains and officers on board are English and Scotch and the sailors Russian.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778. June ?]; Verses. 1p.; ------, -------
    Lines on the refusal by the Church authorities to hold a religious service over Voltaire's remains.
  - to The American Commissioners., [1778. June. 3?]; 3p.; The Sailors on board "The Ranger"
    Petitions for relief from their grievances at the hands of Captain [John Paul] Jones. Praise of Lieutenant Simpson. Mem. S. Ebenezer Watson and seventy-seven others.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June; L. 1p.; Christian Stenger and William Stragham. Brest
    Two captains of merchant vessels hailing from Ireland, captured by the Continental ship "Ranger," petition the American Commissioners to be released and allowed to return to their families.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Comyn, Michel. Marscilles
    Offering his services in the capacity of Consul for the City of Marseilles and requesting Franklin's protection and recommendation to Congress; his experience in trade and his knowledge of French and English. Was instrumental in procuring for the Continental army some officers of distinguished merit, such as the Count Pulaski, and M. le Chevalier de la Baume.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Proceedings of the British Commissioners; they stumbled at the very threshold and in their first communication to Congress advanced a palpable falsehood; if they have nothing further to offer, they have come upon a fool's errand. The cry everywhere is "Independence and fidelity to our treaties." News of the army; General Washington, with 20,000 men, not far from Princeton; Genernal Clinton, with 12 to 15,000, at Mt. Holly. No authentic report of Comte d'Estaing's arrival on the American coast; Boston harbor alive with French vessels and their prizes. Bright prospects for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] July 1; A.L. 2p.; Billon, Mme. Passy
    Witty and bantering reply to Franklin who had compared himself to a beggar asking alms from a bishop. Declines to give Franklin the kind of charity he asks for. Is willing to give him her friendship, considers him as her father but cannot entertain his proposals of love.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Oct., 1906, 37.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Glad that Franklin approves of the use he has made of his letters; only waiting for the news from America promised him by Franklin, to publish it to all Paris. Will do his best to send him the London Evening Post and Chronicle but in the present state of affairs cannot guarantee their arriving regularly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Epp, Charles. Altdorf
    His opinion concerning the strength of the Americans to fight any foreign power; the difficulties that overtake a commonwealth after the enemy has been driven out; the evils to be avoided in a republican government.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 2; L.S. J[ames] Warren. 1p.; The Navy Board of the Eastern Department. Boston
    Sends by the bearer, Captain Ayres, four packets from the Honorable Committee for Foreign Affairs, and the Gazettes of Boston. Recommends Captain Ayres to Franklin's notice as an officer ready upon all occasions to render his best services to his country.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 2; L.S. 3p.; Whipple, Abraham. Nantes
    Acknowledging his favor of the 23d ult. with the agreeable contents. Nearly ready for sea; desires that the necessary merchandise might be put on board as soon as possible. Encloses an exact return of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Godet, Henricus. Amsterdam
    Has been applied to for assistance by one David Welsh, who says he was second lieutenant on board the Lexington, was subsequently taken prisoner, and carried to Plymouth; desires Franklin's orders before he takes any steps in the matter.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Simpson, Thomas. Brest
    Acknowledging the receipt of their favor of the 3d ult. and thanking them for their interposition on his behalf. Has been released from prison by Captain Jones on his signing the enclosed parole. Discusses the question of his passage home; his lack of funds, having received no money since the winter before.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Arrival of the frigate Boston, Captain Tucker, having taken four prizes; Mr. Livingston has set out for Paris to inform them of the disagreeable cause of this vessel's quick return; has undertaken to supply his wants, as Mr. Schweighauser has not had time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 3; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    Thinks it right to keep up the characters of the men in power, though their conduct has in general seemed unintelligible and to have no bottom but courtiership and pride. Believes America will feel with England in her distress and not let France and Spain push her to the wall; acknowledges England's weakness and believes it probable that the French will land and even stay for a season. Lord Bute's desire to come into power with Lord Chatham and the latter's repudiation of him. Franklin's opinion of Lord Chatham erroneous. Private business matters. Messages to Mr. Williams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Fairholme and Luther. Isle de Ré
    No answer received to their two letters, announcing the arrival at Isle de Ré of an English prize, and offering to act for Congress in this and similar matters; desire the necessary orders.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.